This is Robert Sheer with another edition of Sheer Intelligence, it's actually my alternative
to the Central Intelligence Agency and by coincidence our guest today is John Kiriako who was sort of
a hero at the Central Intelligence Agency where he worked for almost 15 years and he
overlapped the events of 9-11 and it was John Kiriako who was in charge of counter-terrorism
operations in Pakistan and as an Arabic speaker and very knowledgeable in the region who was
involved in the capture of the most important, at that time most important Al Qaeda operative
supposed to have been the number 3-1 Abu Zubedah and the interesting question here is the effectiveness
of torture and the nominee from President Trump to be the new head of the CIA, Gina Haspel has
been referred to some including John Kiriako as bloody Gina because during that period she was a
deputy director of counter-terrorism activities and she was involved in not only conducting
these torture experiments and practices in Thailand and elsewhere but she is also accused
of having destroyed 92 tapes that were supposed to be released about the torture program which
don't exist now so why don't you bring us up to date we're doing this interview while she's
still the nominee and what is your view of that nomination and where do you think it's going
to end up? First of all thanks for having me Bob it's always a pleasure to speak with you I
enjoy these conversations a great deal and I think this is a very very important issue
I've been writing about this and speaking about this extensively I did an op-ed in the
Washington Post last week I feel very very strongly about this nominee and my feeling is
that it's a wonderful wonderful thing that the president wants to name a woman as the director
of the CIA but that woman ought not to be Gina Haspel there are probably 50 women across government
across the intelligence community who would be well qualified highly qualified and would
probably be terrific directors of the CIA but Gina Haspel should be disqualified for her past
at the very top of the CIA's illegal torture program well why don't you bring us up to date
on that because you know yes some people are even saying you should support her because she is a
woman and you know there are other people saying she just was following orders and what
have you and you've written quite critically of that practice of exonerating torture so what's
going on here are we have we come to see torture as American as apple pie I know a group of defense
intellectuals who opposed torture have cited polls saying that a majority of Americans now
think it's an efficient tool to make us more secure we seem to be the major force in the
world justifying torture these days so what's happened here yeah that's that's a shame too because
the torture issue has become very partisan a huge majority of republicans supports the
torture program and a huge majority of democrats opposes the torture program so let's get a couple
of our of our historical facts out on the table at first in 1946 bob we executed Japanese
soldiers who had waterboarded American prisoners of war during the second world war
it wasn't called waterboarding then it was called water torture or the water treatment
but it was waterboarding plain and simple and that was deemed to be a death penalty offense
in january of 1968 the washington post ran a front page photograph of an american soldier
waterboarding a north vietnamese prisoner of war on the day that that photo was published
the secretary of defense robert macnamara ordered an investigation the soldier was arrested he was
charged with torture he was convicted and he was sentenced to 20 years in leavenworth well
between 1946 and now the law never changed waterboarding and other forms of torture
were illegal in 1946 they were illegal in 1968 and john uh you and j byby's memo uh from the justice
department in 2002 notwithstanding waterboarding was still illegal in 2002 so you know to me
we are conceding our leadership position on international human rights and we have decided
as a matter of policy that whatever is expedient is okay because we're the good guys
and so we can do whatever we want and that's just simply wrong i mean clearly we're hardly the good
guys in wars like iraq that you that's right i know about which we're done without any justification
fake data which by the way was supposed to have been collected in part by torture and it was
false data but but the argument that and it's interesting and and the defensive torture the
public has changed on this and partially that's due of course of of hollywood and mass media and it
will be like zero dark 30 which we're where the cia took hollywood director catlin bill glow and her
screenwriters and others into their confidence actually betrayed national security by giving
them the names of navy seals who were later involved in the capture bin laden and somehow
got hollywood to endorse or that part of hollywood to endorse the idea of torture
as efficient but you know from your own experience that it's been exactly the opposite it created
bad information so why don't you tell us about the example of your own capture of abu zubeda and
and and what you learned about the whole process sure we captured abu zubeda in uh march late
march of 2002 he had been shot and severely wounded shot by a pakistani policeman with an ak-47
in the thigh the groin in the stomach he was very gravely injured and we held him in pakistan for about
four days three and a half days after he was captured and i i spent 54 consecutive hours
with him just the two of us in his hospital room i had tied him to his bed because i was
afraid that i would fall asleep and he would somehow escape when he finally came out of
this coma after he was shot we we began conversing and we talked about a lot of things we talked about
the september 11 attacks we talked about uh his family uh he had been writing poetry he wanted
to recite poetry we talked about um christianity and islam we talked about a lot of different
things well i told him that uh and i said it very plainly i said listen i'm the nicest guy
that you're going to encounter in this in this experience my colleagues are not as nice as i am
so if i can give you one piece of advice it's this it's that you have to cooperate because
your life is over so the rest of it can be terrible or it can be okay it's up to you
i urge you to cooperate and he said to me you seem like a nice man but you're the enemy
and i'll never cooperate well i said suit yourself in the meantime a cia jet came in in the middle of
the night three fbi agents and i picked him up uh on a gurney and we carried him out to the plane
we took him to the back of the plane and strapped him down to the luggage rack and i said to him
remember you have to cooperate and he squeezed my hand i never saw him again but what happened
subsequently is really what lays the foundation of this entire debate and that is when he arrived at
his uh secret prison site that's been discussed extensively in the press he was too severely
wounded to be interrogated so the cia gave him about six weeks to recover from his wounds
at the end of that six week period an fbi agent by the name of ali sufan began to
interrogate him and ali sufan used a tried and true fbi technique and that technique is just simply
to establish a rapport with your subject to to establish a relationship to the point where
your prisoner feels comfortable enough that he inevitably will open up to you and will begin
talking well that's exactly what happened ali sufan engaged abu zubeda in conversation
he offered him some dates he offered him a cigarette or an orange or whatever it was
and over the period of several weeks abu zubeda began to open up and he gave ali sufan what ali
later described as actionable intelligence that was used to disrupt future attacks and to save
american lives well the cia for whatever reason decided that this was taking too long the cia
had convinced itself that there was another attack that was imminent and the only way to get the
information on that attack was to torture abu zubeda and so in july of 2002 george tenet who
was the director of the cia at the time went to president bush and asked president bush to move
authority over abu zubeda from the fbi
to the CIA. Now usually overseas the CIA has primacy and domestically the FBI has
primacy but because the September 11th attacks were still considered to be an
open criminal investigation the FBI had primacy in this case. Now for whatever
reason and he's never explained this President Bush decided to do just that
and to transfer primacy from the FBI to the CIA that happened on August the
1st 2002 within two hours of that transfer of primacy the CIA began to
torture Abu Zubaydah and he immediately clammed up. Now when I say torture there
were 10 separate techniques that were supposed to be used on Abu Zubaydah and
the CIA officers implementing this program were supposed to start with the
mildest technique and that was grabbing him by the lapels giving him
a shake and yelling at him to answer their questions but they didn't do that they
start they started with some of the roughest techniques the first one was
called walling where a prisoner is supposed to have a towel wrapped around
his neck and he slammed into into a wall a wooden wall in order to
frighten him it makes a loud sound your head slams against the wall it's
it's shocking the problem is is that Abu Zubaydah was never given a towel
around his neck and he was slammed into a concrete wall we know from other
prisoners who were subjected to walling that they have suffered permanent brain
damage from this technique later that very same day Abu Zubaydah was water
boarded for the first time for the first of 83 times so he became so
enraged that he just stopped talking all together and the more the CIA
tortured him the angrier he became but he refused to cooperate finally the
torturers who who were two contract psychologists named Mitchell and
Jessen decided that they needed to bring Ali Sufran back into the country so
Ali Sufran and an FBI contingent flew back to this secret location it took
Ali another two or three weeks to reestablish that rapport and again
Abu Zubaydah began to talk now we know from the Senate torture report that the
information that he gave Ali Sufran was this it was not about impending
attacks and it wasn't because Abu Zubaydah didn't know anything about
any impending attacks the information that the CIA had that Abu Zubaydah was
the number three in Al Qaeda was just simply false he wasn't the number
three in Al Qaeda in fact he had never actually joined Al Qaeda he
wanted to and he ran Al Qaeda safe house and he established Al Qaeda's two training
camps in southern Afghanistan he was a bad man but he was not the number three
in Al Qaeda and he was not privy to the kind of information that the number
three would have as you pointed out before the FBI actually took a strong
position against being involved in the torture and they were far more
effective in getting information but what I want to get at in the current
situation with CIA deputy director Gina Hasbow who's been nominated to take over
this agency she was there when he was I mean she was on top of this area she
was the chief of staff for the counterterrorism center run by Rodriguez
who was the guy who's sort of the author of the whole torture program so she
knew this was going on then and absolutely that's the big issue the
U.S. Congress has to face do they want to put in charge a person in charge of the
CIA who had full knowledge and I'm assuming you're saying that she had
full knowledge of the torture program so she knew about all of it the
waterboarding the slamming that stress positions the coffins the whole thing
and she goes back what to 1985 in the CIA she's been there what 35 years or
34 years and and so and she was in charge of this program yeah she was
in charge of this program now there's some dispute the CIA is disputing that
she was actually there at the secret site on the day that I was a beta was
tortured but that's not even the issue we know that she was there on the day
that Abdulahim initially was tortured and she oversaw his torture but
you're right Bob she was she was this the chief of staff in the CIA's
counterterrorism center as a deputy to the notorious Jose Rodriguez who was
the creator of the CIA's torture program and I'll tell you another thing you
know I spent I spent two and a half years on Capitol Hill as as the senior
investigator on the Senate Foreign Relations Committee and I have several
friends who are still in place at at the Foreign Relations Committee and at
the Intelligence Committee and one of them told me just today that Gina
Haspel has been meeting with all the senators who are members of the
Senate Intelligence Committee and she has been promising them that if they
approve of her nomination if she's confirmed she's promising that she will
not break the law well if you have to go out on a limb and promise that you're
not going to break the law because in previous years that's exactly what you've
done you've broken the law then I think we need somebody else as CIA director
who's not going to have this baggage hanging over her head time for a
break in my conversation with former CIA agent John Kiriakou and we'll be right back
we're back with John Kiriakou a 15-year veteran the CIA who went to prison for
telling the American public that there was indeed a waterboarding torture
program well let's talk about breaking the law because this is the
people don't realize that we signed off on on international conventions and we
also under Ronald Reagan actually passed a law right a banning torture we've got
the federal torture act which goes back to 1946 and specifically bans exactly
those techniques that the CIA used and then you're right in 1988 under the
Reagan administration we were the primary drafters and original
signatories of the United Nations Convention Against Torture that treaty
was ratified in 1994 and as such has the the force of domestic law and so we've
got two concurrent laws then that specifically ban exactly those techniques
that the CIA was using now don't forget that just because the Bush Justice
Department said that these techniques were legal that they were legal because
they had never been presented to a court of law this was a classified a highly
classified top secret legal opinion that allowed the CIA they thought to go ahead
with this torture program if they had gone to court it would have clearly
and quickly been invalidated as illegal yeah and it should be pointed out as
you have pointed out and so you're writing there's the Nuremberg principle
where the defense that the Germans were following orders right not accepted and
they were executed for following orders that you know violated the fundamental
rights of human beings and I do want to stress here that these conversations
that Gina Haspel has been having with members of you know the House and
Senate Intelligence Committees and going around getting approval they
must have known I mean people like Diane Feinstein the Democrats we're talking
about now on the Senate committee Adam Schiff on the House Intelligence
Committee they must have known for a long time about the torture after all
the Senate report was five years in the making we still haven't gotten to read
the report on torture what we have is the executive summary and that's
enough to make an indictment of it but this whole idea that somehow
you can be involved in such a nefarious program and then you're
appointed to be head of the agency you point out you're writing
this ends a hell of a signal of what's acceptable on on the highest level
it sends a signal that it's okay to break the law not only is it okay
but you can get promoted after breaking the law and indeed you can be named
director of the CIA well I just want to say in terms of breaking the law
people should understand specifically there had been a directive that the 92
hours of videos of this torture program which were very specific should be
preserved as as necessary evidence to what had happened and that
according to your writing Gina Haspel was instrumental in the destruction of
that evidence evidence of serious felony she personally wrote and
transmitted the cable from CIA headquarters to the secret site
ordering the chief of base to destroy those tapes
to destroy evidence of the torture Jose Rodriguez later said
in his memoir for which he received a four million dollar advance I might add
that he had ordered her to order the destruction of the tapes not because he
was obstructing justice of course not because he was trying to cover up a
crime of course but because he knew that eventually these these tapes would
leak out and people would would judge them out of context and come to a
false conclusion about the CIA and that's ludicrous that's interesting because
he received a four million dollar advance and you received two years in
federal prison after you know what 15 years of
honorable service you were highly awarded you were involved in what was
then the capture of the highest known kind of operative who was captured
and you in 207 made a statement acknowledging the water boarding
program. This was after you were out of the agency. And in fact, the Republican at that
time, George W. Bush, their Justice Department didn't bring charges against you. They were
investigated and they would decide you operated within the law. It was only under Barack Obama
when he did his kind of crusade against whistleblowers that you were singled out and you ended
up because you gave the name of a not an undercover but a known CIA person to a New
York Times reporter that you had to serve two years in federal prison.
Yeah, ironically, I was convicted of violating the Intelligence Identities Protection Act
of 1981. I confirmed the last name of a former colleague who was retired to a journalist.
The journalist never made the name public. And so I was charged with a myriad of felonies,
at the time. Later on, the director of the CIA, David Petraeus, exposed the names of 10
undercover CIA officers to his girlfriend who was writing his biography. And he was charged
with a misdemeanor and was given 18 months of probation and a $100,000 fine. You mentioned
that the Bush administration had concluded that I had not committed a crime. That's
true. And so the Bush administration in December of 2008 closed the case and said I had not
committed a crime. They went so far as to send what's called a declination letter to
my attorneys where they declined to prosecute me. But what I did not know was that a month
later in January of 2009, when President Obama was inaugurated, that the CIA asked
him to secretly reopen the case against me. And he did. And so I had no idea that for the
next three years, my phones were tapped, my emails were being intercepted. I had three
different teams of FBI agents surveilling me and following me. And then finally in
January of 2012, I was charged with these five felonies and facing 45 years in prison,
which is essentially a death penalty. I agreed to take a plea to this lesser charge to make
this thing go away.
You're the one person that suffers time in jail for having revealed the existence of
a torture program. And now Gina Haspel is on the verge of being rewarded with being
head of the director of the leading intelligence agency in the world, the most powerful.
And we're being asked as a public to ignore her involvement in this torture program. And
I was wondering, you worked in the Senate with John Kerry, his committee, he hired you,
you know, your master's thesis was on the legislative process, and you work with a whole
bunch of defense intellectuals and former intelligence officials who have condemned
this torture. And Senator John McCain, himself, was held as a prisoner in North Vietnam,
condemned this behavior. What response are you getting? Are they telling you that we should
look the other way because Gina Haspel is sorry for what she did or she's a woman or it doesn't
matter? What are you hearing?
I'm sad to tell you that, yes, for the most part, most of the people that I'm engaging
with are saying we need to move on from this. And I'll tell you where I've been
the most disappointed too. Number one, Chuck Schumer, the Senate minority leader, announced
last week that he would not whip votes for this confirmation hearing. And what that means
is that he is not instructing Democratic senators to vote against Gina Haspel. He's telling them
that they can vote their conscience. Well, when you have five Democrats running for reelection
in states that Donald Trump won by at least 10 percentage points, that means go ahead
and vote yes on Gina Haspel. So right off the top, the vote is probably lost.
The only hope I think that we have are people like Rand Paul, who not only announced that
he would vote no, but also announced that he would filibuster Gina Haspel's nomination.
That's a no.
Rand Paul, the Republican and Libertarian Senator from Kentucky, who was opposed to
the war in Iraq and from the beginning anyway, and many of these foreign adventures.
But let me ask you about your grasp on reality here. Is any of something incredibly
shocking? You are somebody who were punished, as I said, for revealing torture. We've signed
these international agreements, even under a sort of hawkish president like Ronald Reagan,
against torture. And yet we're about to anoint this woman to be head of our most secret
program, who is what you call a bloody Gina, but she certainly has bloody hands in
this respect. And in terms of, again, these senators and so forth, I mean, they might want
to get reelected, but what's going on here? How did torture, you signed some of your articles
that there's a popular support for torture. How did this come to be?
I remember in 2007 seeing a poll that said that a majority of Americans opposed torturing
prisoners, but a majority of Americans supported killing them. And I remember being appalled
by that. We were supposed to be a nation of laws. We're supposed to be a nation of law
and order and respect for the Constitution. And when you capture people and you torture
them and you hold them in communicado for decades at a secret prison where even the
Red Cross doesn't have access, that's not respect for the rule of law. And you
know, how do we go to our allies and friends around the world with a straight face every
year when we write the State Department's a congressionally mandated human rights report
and we tell them, you have to respect international human rights. And then they say to us, but
you don't respect human rights. So, you know, I talked to a foreign diplomat just recently
and he said that he had an almost surreal experience where he had a State Department
officer come into his office and essentially scold him and say, you have to respect international
human rights. And when that State Department officer left his office, a CIA officer walked
into the office and said, listen, we want to send a prisoner over to your place. We
want you to, you know, manhandle him and let us know what he says.
And the person who ran those programs of rendition, sending those prisoners to
be tortured in Egypt and Thailand and all sorts of places, that is the woman that was
nominated by our president to be the new director of the CIA, Gina Haspel. And you make
a pretty serious charge. You actually say this woman was not some bystander or a lower
level official, but she was the number two person running the torture program.
That's right. She was. She was the number two. And again, the message to the CIA workforce is
that you don't have to respect the law. The message is that you don't have to
respect the oversight committees because the oversight committees are largely cheerleaders
or lemmings and they'll do as they're told to do. And we see this proven time and time again.
One of my attorneys spoke recently with Senator Ron Wyden of Oregon
to ask him if he was going to join in the filibuster with Rand Paul against the Gina
Haspel nomination. And Wyden responded, look, I'd like to, but it takes all my energy
just to not lose my security clearance. And so to me, that's not leadership.
That's not oversight. That's allowing the CIA to set the agenda. And then
the overseers are commanded to fall into line. And time and time again, they do.
We should be clear about Ron Wyden is a guy that, you know, I've certainly long respected.
He's been one of the few individuals on the Senate Intelligence Committee who's
actually brought up the issue of torture. And you have people, Diane Feinstein is given credit
because she was the chair of the Committee, although for five years she knew about
the torture. Didn't tell us about it. But nonetheless, they printed a heavily redacted
form of it. We've never actually seen the report. You have people, again,
on the House side Intelligence Committee like Adam Schiff, who are very concerned about foreign
governments, you know, killing people in their secret agencies where they form agent in England
and the part of Putin's Russia and so forth. And yet you're basically saying these intelligence
agencies that are supposed to be monitoring the CIA and holding it accountable are in fact puppets
of it. Oh, they are puppets. You know, I remember at the height of the torture program,
I was working still working in the CIA's counterterrorism center. And I remember Jane Harmon
coming to the building for briefings. And these were very high level, very, you know,
several compartments above top secret briefings on this program. And then when it was finally
exposed in 2007, she denied any knowledge of it. Well, I knew that that was a bald faced lie,
just like when Nancy Pelosi denied that she had any knowledge of it. That was also a lie.
Why was it alive? Nancy Pelosi, who we maybe think of as a great liberal, right? Well, Nancy Pelosi
at the time was was the the House, what was it minority leader, I suppose, or majority leader,
one or the other. And she had been personally briefed on the CIA's torture program personally
briefed. The people who were briefed were the Speaker of the House, the majority leader,
the minority leader, the minority whip, and the chairman and vice chairman of the two committees.
So she was personally briefed. Now her her defense, when this was finally made public,
was she may have been invited
to the briefing but she probably left before the really bloody information was conveyed
and the assistant who had stayed behind to take notes apparently didn't brief her.
Well that's just nonsense because staff members were not privy to this information.
There was no staff member there taking notes. She was briefed, she walked out,
she didn't do anything to stop the torture program and then she denied any knowledge of it.
Is this true of Dianne Feinstein as well? Another absolutely yes. Democratic,
somewhat liberal leader? Well-known cheerleader for the CIA, Dianne Feinstein. I'll tell you another
thing about Dianne Feinstein. When Barack Obama was flailing around looking for a CIA director,
you remember there were three or four people who were who were proposed and who
ended up never being able to make it through confirmation. Dianne Feinstein said that
she would vote yes for whomever President Obama wanted to name so long as Steve Kappus was named
deputy director. So Steve Kappus had been the acting director. He had been the deputy director for
operations, highly, highly respected, very professional officer, but he was also instrumental
in the torture program. He was the deputy director for operations when the torture
program was being carried out. So why in the world would Dianne Feinstein,
if she was opposed to torture, demand, insist that one of the highest ranking officers involved
in the torture program be named the CIA's deputy director? It just doesn't make any sense at all.
So what is finally your opinion of what we learned from the torture report and how does it relate
to Gina Haspel? Tell us about the torture report because what we have is the executive summary,
again, heavily redacted. That's right. We've got a heavily redacted 500-page executive summary
of a report that is supposed to be 5,000 to 7,000 pages long. Now, I've said this before.
I'm going to say it again because it's very important. If you look at the executive summary
that's been released and published, and it's available free now online thanks to the Haspel
nomination, pay very close and special attention to the footnotes because that's where the real story
is. If you read the footnotes, you'll be able to figure out the entire story. And the story is
that Gina Haspel was involved in this program up to her neck. And one of the objections that I
have to this nomination is that she had multiple opportunities over the course of several years
to say no, to say this is wrong, it's illegal, it's unconstitutional, it's unethical and immoral.
And she never said any of that. She said, yes, sir, when told to destroy the tapes. Yes, sir,
when told to fly to the secret site to be chief of the torture program there.
She could have said no, and she didn't.
I want to thank you, John Kuriyaku, a 15-year veteran of the CIA who was rewarded for his
patriotic service and telling the American people the truth by putting an extent to
federal prison and commenting on a woman who ran the program. And it may now be rewarded with
being head of the CIA. So thanks for coming. Thanks for having me. It's always a pleasure
speaking with you. Our producers for the show, KCRW, are Rebecca Mooney and Josh Shear,
our engineers are Kat Yor and Mario Diaz. See you next week for another edition of Shear Intelligence.